so let's look at the solution to our
consistency quiz where we have coherent
memory
but an out of order pair of cores where
branches are predicted stores are still
done strictly in program order but loads
can be reordered and these two variables
start at zero what the programmer is
kind of expected to happen is that i put
some values in some data then i set a
flag and the other core waits for that
flag to be set
so that it can print the data that i
produced so in program order the only
thing that can really happen is that we
print 15. in the execution order
that can also happen
if this score gets to this part before
we even start checking we might compute
15 in the data set flag to 1 core 1
loops here
sees that the flag is 1 exits prints 15.
so clearly 15 is possible but the
question is can we get anything else
these are done strictly in order so if
anything else does get printed it's not
going to be because this score
did the data right after the flag was
set the flag actually gets it after the
writes are complete
but here's what can happen
this loop here amounts to reading the
flag testing if it's zero and then
branching based on that
this processor can easily predict this
branch
in a way that says
we exit
before it even gets to check what the
flag was
so at that point we will be here
and we will fetch the data to be printed
the data at that point
might be zero so what we do is we
predict it goes out and we fetch the
data at this point so it's kind of step
one predict and leave the loop step two
read the data and it's zero at this
point then let's say core two finishes
this
and at that point this out of order
processor does this load remember these
are loads they can be reordered if we do
this
we see that the flag at this point is
one
so our prediction was correct
and at this point we can print the data
that we found
in this case we will print zero a
similar outcome is possible for data
equal stance simply by moving this here
so we can also print 10 if access number
which reads the date after the
prediction of the branch
happens here and finally we could get 15
in the data if we get it here but we
already knew we could get 15. note that
it's not possible to get 5 or anything
else
and the reason is that these writes on
the same core will happen in program
order it's incorrect for a core to
somehow read 0 here because the only way
we read data here
is if
it was already written here on the same
core we have to obey the program order
that was never in question
so the data when it's read here has to
be 10 we can only increment it by 5 to
15 we cannot read 0 here
so that's why it's possible only to get
0 10 or 15. so basically the real
problem is that somehow
although we thought we are waiting for
the flag to be set before we access the
data in reality we managed to access the
data at kind of any point before the
flag was set
and coherence again didn't prevent this
what we need is consistency